ICAT RESTful interface

Introduction

ICAT provides both a SOAP and a RESTful web service to communicate with the core ICAT code which makes calls to a relational DBMS. This document describes the RESTful interface but assumes some knowledge of ICAT as explained in the ICAT Java Client manual.

For each call the Java annotations in the server code are shown as these indicate precisely what is expected. @POST, @PUT, @DELETE and @GET denote the method and @Path shows the relative url path. They are all relative to "icat". The @Consumes and @Produces shows the expected format of the body of the message.

The @GET calls can be tried on a web browser and curl can be used to make any of the calls. For example a url of the form: https://example.com:443/icat/version will return some json such as {"version":"4.4.0"}

In the case of an error from the ICAT code the returned json will be of the form: {"code":"BAD_PARAMETER", "message":"password too short", "offset":"0"} where the offset will be omitted when it is not useful. It is to show how many entities would have been succesfully processed if a subsequent error had not occured. The status code will correspond to the type of the ICAT exception as shown by the code value. In the case of any other error, the returned json will be of the form: {"code":"INTERNAL", "message":"null pointer exception"} and the status code will be 500 ("Internal Server Error"). Clients should check the status code and if status/100 is not 2 then an error has occured.

This document is divided into sections covering

Session management
Entity management
Import and Export
Miscellaneous

Session management

login

To obtain a new session.

@POST
@Path("session")
@Consumes(MediaType.APPLICATION_FORM_URLENCODED)
@Produces(MediaType.APPLICATION_JSON)

The form parameter is:

jsonString
which takes the form {"plugin":"db", "credentials[{"username":"root"}, {"password":"guess"}]}

The returned json is of the form {"sessionId","0d9a3706-80d4-4d29-9ff3-4d65d4308a24"}

getSession

To obtain information about a session.

@GET
@Path("session/{sessionId}")
@Produces(MediaType.APPLICATION_JSON)

The path parameter is:

sessionId
which takes the form 0d9a3706-80d4-4d29-9ff3-4d65d4308a24

The returned json is of the form {"userName":"db/root","remainingMinutes":117.87021666666666}

refresh

To refresh a session.

@PUT
@Path("session/{sessionId}")

The path parameter is:

sessionId
which takes the form 0d9a3706-80d4-4d29-9ff3-4d65d4308a24

logout

To logout - i.e. delete a session.

@DELETE
@Path("session/{sessionId}")

The path parameter is:

sessionId
which takes the form 0d9a3706-80d4-4d29-9ff3-4d65d4308a24

Entity management

create

To create one or more entities in ICAT

@POST
@Path("entityManager")
@Consumes(MediaType.APPLICATION_FORM_URLENCODED)
@Produces(MediaType.APPLICATION_JSON) public String

The form parameters are:

sessionId
which takes the form 0d9a3706-80d4-4d29-9ff3-4d65d4308a24
entities
which takes the form [{"InvestigationType":{"facility":{"id":12042},"name":"ztype"}},{"Facility":{"name":"another fred"}}] . It is a list of objects where each object has a name which is the type of the entity and a value which is an object with name value pairs where these names are the names of the attributes and the values are either simple or they may be objects themselves. In this case two entities are being created an InvestigationType and a Facility with a name of "another fred". The InvestigationType being created will reference an existing facility with an id of 12042 and will have a name of "ztype". For references to existing objects only the "id" value need be set otherwise if child objects are to be created at the same time then the "id" should not be set but the other desired attributes should.

The returned json is of the form [125, 126] and is a list of the ids of the objects created.

search

To search for information in ICAT. This includes the functionality of both search and get calls in the SOAP web service.

@GET @Produces(MediaType.APPLICATION_JSON)
@Path("entityManager")

The query parameters are:

sessionId
which takes the form 0d9a3706-80d4-4d29-9ff3-4d65d4308a24
query
which takes the form SELECT f FROM Facility f
id
which takes the form 732 and is used when the functionality of get is required in which case the query must be as described in the ICAT Java Client manual.

The returned json is of the form [{"Facility":{"id":126, "name":"another fred"}}] and is a list of the objects returned and takes the same form as the data passed in for create. If an id value is specified then only one object can be returned so the outer square brackets are omitted.

Import and Export

The import and export calls make use of a special format to represent ICAT data efficiently. The file may contain line starting with a # sign. The first non-comment line contains the version number of the file format with major and minor parts. Each entity type is preceded by a blank line line followed by a one line entity descriptor and then a line for each entity of that type. For example:

 #  Version of file format
 1.0
 
 Facility ( name:0, daysUntilRelease:1, createId:2, createTime:3)
 "Test port facility", 90, "Zorro", 1920-05-16T16:58:26.12Z
 
 InvestigationType (facility(name:0), name:1)
 "Test port facility", "atype"
 "Test port facility", "btype"
 
 Investigation(facility(name:0), name:1, visitId:2, type(facility(name:0), name:3), title:4)
 "Test port facility", "expt1", "one", "atype", "a title"

The entity descriptor starts with the name of the entity type followed by a comma separated list attribute of field names held inside parentheses. It is not necessary to include those which you don't wish to set as any that are not present and are allowed to be null will be set to null when importing. So we see that this file will create a Facility with fields: name, daysUntilRelease, createId and createTime. Following the field name is a colon and an integer showing the offset to the data field in each of the next set of rows. So a facility will be created with a name of "Test port facility" and with 90 daysUntilRelease. All strings must be enclosed in double quotes and to represent a double quote within the string then two double quotes must be used. True, false and null literals are not case sensitive. The last two fields of the facility are createId and createTime. If you specify that you want all attributes and you are a "root user" then the values of createId and createTime will be respected otherwise the current time is used and the id is that of the user doing the import. Timestamps literals follow ISO 8601 and support fractional seconds and time zones. If the time zone is omitted it is interpreted as local time.

Now consider the InvestigationType for which we need to specify the facility to which it belongs and its name. The facility cannot be descibed by its id because we don't know what it is. So instead we list in parentheses the field names that define it. So name:0 is the name of the facility and name:1 is the name of the InvestigationType.

The next line shows the convenience of this syntax. The investigation has a facility (identified by its name:0) and the name:1 of the investigation and the visitId but it also has a type which is identified a facility (identified by its name:0) and by the name:3 of the type. Finally it has a title:4 field. Note that name:0 is used twice as in this case the inverstigation belongs to the same facility as its type. This works fine as long as we deal with entity types which have key fields. This is shown in the next snippet from an import file:

 DataCollection(?:0)
 "a"
 "b"
 "c"
 
 DataCollectionDatafile(datafile(dataset(investigation(facility(name:0), name:1, visitId:2), name:3), name:4), dataCollection(?:5))
 "Test port facility", "expt1", "one", "ds1", "df1",  "a"
 "Test port facility", "expt1", "one", "ds1", "df2",  "b"
 
 Job(application(facility(name:0), name:1, version:2), inputDataCollection(?:3), outputDataCollection(?:4))
 "Test port facility", "aprog", "1.2.3", "a", "b"

Here we have the DataCollection which we imagine to be indentified by the anonymous variable "?". This section of the file will create three DataCollection entries which we shall remember for the duration of the import process as "a", "b" and "c". DataCollectionDatafiles are then associated with DataCollections "a" and "b" and a job is created with one DataCollection as input and one as output. When performing export the same format is used however some values will be repeated - for example the facility name will appear many times in most rows.

import

Import data into ICAT

@Path("port")
@POST
@Consumes(MediaType.MULTIPART_FORM_DATA)

The multipart form data starts with a form parameter with a ContentType of TEXT_PLAIN and a name of "json" and is followed by the data to be imported with a ContentType of APPLICATION_OCTET_STREAM.

The json takes the form: "{sessionId", "0d9a3706-80d4-4d29-9ff3-4d65d4308a24", "duplicate", "THROW", "attributes", "USER"} . The value "duplicate" if not specified defaults to "THROW". It is not case sensitive and it defines the action to be taken if a duplicate is found:

THROW
throw an exception
IGNORE
go to the next row
CHECK
check that new data matches the old - and throw exception if it does not.
OVERWRITE
replace old data with new

The value "attributes" if not specified defaults to "USER". It is not case sensitive and it defines which attributes to consider:

USER
values for modId, createId, modDate and createDate provided in the input will be ignored.
ALL
all field values specified will be respected. This option is only available to those specified in the rootUserNames in the icat.properties file.

export

Export data from ICAT

@Path("port")
@GET @Path("port")
@Produces(MediaType.TEXT_PLAIN)

The query parameter is:

json
which takes the form {"sessionId":"0d9a3706-80d4-4d29-9ff3-4d65d4308a24","query":"Facility", , "attributes":"ALL" where query if specified is a normal ICAT query which may have an INCLUDE clause. This is used to define the metadata to export. If not present then the whole ICAT will be exported.

The value "attributes" if not specified defaults to "USER". It is not case sensitive and it defines which attributes to consider:

USER
values for modId, createId, modDate and createDate will not appear in the output.
ALL
all field values will be output.

The response is the requested export data.

Miscellaneous

version

Return the version of the ICAT server

@Path("version")
@GET @Produces(MediaType.APPLICATION_JSON)

The returned json is of the form: {"version":"4.4.0"}

ICAT Server Release Notes

4.9.2

Bug fixes

Create a new option to configure which entities are included in the Lucene index. For example, remove 'Datafile' and 'DatafileParameter' if the number of datafiles exceeds lucene's limit of 2^32 entries in an index lucene.entitiesToIndex = Datafile Dataset Investigation InvestigationUser DatafileParameter DatasetParameter InvestigationParameter Sample
Upgrade the Apache HttpClient from 4.3.4 to 4.3.6 because of a security vulnerability (CVE-2015-5262).
Changes to tests and the default developer configuration to remove references to Steve Fisher's computer.

4.9.1

Bug fixes

Restore the documentation for the RESTful API
Add to run.properties: lucene.directory, lucene.backlogHandlerIntervalSeconds and lucene.enqueuedRequestIntervalSecond to deal with batching requests to icat.lucene. This greatly improves ingest performance.

4.9.0

Add SOAP call getAuthenticatorInfo, support of authenticator and lucene services and bug fixes

Simplify output from REST properties call
Add SOAP call getAuthenticatorInfo
Add SOAP call getVersion() which is identical to getApiVersion()
Updated property file names to run.properties and setup.properties
run.properties no longer has the logback.xml property. Any logback.xml file in the installation directory will be applied but will not be copied to the config directory. There is a logback.xml.example file in the distribution which can be copied to logback.xml and edited.
An authenticator may be a restful web service rather than a possibly remote EJB.
The lucene calls are now handled by a separate server allowing deployment of more than one ICAT to share a single lucene server. Most of the lucene configuration has been moved to the lucene server.
Fix bug in update which was making it very slow when lucene was enabled
Works with Payara but has intermittent problems with Glassfish 4.0 and 4.1.1 so please use payara41.
Synchronization of public tables and public steps is now done by restful calls rather than JMS. This means that the run.properties file needs a list of other servers to synchronize with.

4.8.0

Support update operations with control on individual attributes and bug fixes

Protect the SOAP interface from bad plugin mnemonics on login calls
Support update operations with control on individual attributes
The testicat program has been recoded to use only REST calls.
A new clone operation has been added to the REST interface
A new property "key" may be specified in the icat.properties file. If there is an IDS server in use and it has a key for digest protection of Datafile.location then this key value must be identical.

4.7.0

Enhanced Rest interface and changes to the authorization code

A restful select can mention multiple quantities to be returned
A major re-write of the authorization code should make it more efficient in most cases as all the work is carried out by the database unless the INCLUDE mechanism is used. This has required that the Rule table has a slightly different structure from 4.6.0 so the correct upgrade procedure from earlier versions must be followed.
COUNT queries will not fail because they are counting more than maxEntities values
A couple of bugs in eclipse link result in incorrect information being returned. One of these bugs was trapped previously but with the generality of the queries now supported it has become impractical to trap.

"SELECT f from Facility WHERE f.id = 1 LIMIT 1,10" which should always return an empty list now ignores the LIMIT clause.
"SELECT ds.complete FROM Dataset ds" only returns the false values but that "SELECT ds.id, ds.complete FROM Dataset ds" works properly.

A restful delete call has been added
The delete(Many) call, whether restful or not, checks the authz rules for all objects that will be deleted by the cascade mechanism.
A restful write call to do both create(Many) and update(Many) has been written. Notifications are sent for all objects created and/or updated. Authz is also applied to all new or updated entries.
Notifications are no longer generated for deletes as the information could never be used. This means that only C and U are valid notification letters in the icat.properties file.
DataCollection now has a doi attribute
Call logging has been changed to generate only jms messages. It is very similar to the call logging in the IDS. It is controlled by a log.list in the icat.properties which may contain one or more of READ, WRITE, SESSION and INFO.
Updates whether from the SOAP call or the restful write call are both checked for UPDATE permission before the call and if a relationship field is changed which is used to identify that object then DELETE permission is required before the change and CREATE permission afterwards.
Added attributes email and orcidId to the User table
testicat and icatadmin have certificate checking disabled. This used to be the normal behaviour but newer version of python, by default, expect a certificate accessible by openssl.
Produce an error message rather than a null pointer exception if an invalid authenticator mnemonic is used in a login call.
Added "isLogedIn" REST call
Fixed bug when trying to read or write ParameterValueType values (an enum) through REST call. These are now represented as json string values.
Fixed bug trying to read back an individual date value through a REST call.
Remove db.vendor and add db.target and db.logging to icat-setup.properties.
The jdbc driver jar if present in the domain's lib directory must be moved to lib/ext.

4.6.1

Bug fix release

Previously the update call failed if a Datafile was passed in with all datafileCreateTime, datafileModTime and modTime all set to null. If the Datafile was fetched, modified in memory and then update was called then modTime would be set and the problem would not reveal itself.
It should also be noted that from release 4.6.0 Java 8 is required to run the code.

4.6.0

Small change to icat.properties

notification.list and log.list may now be omitted but must not be present and empty in the icat.properties file
Provide a "getProperties()" restful call to find out what can be revealed about a server without a sessionId. This includes maxEntities and information about the available authenticators.
Support the ESCAPE keyword in JPQL queries.
New calls added to the restful interface for lucene queries.
Documentation for the restful interface is now generated by MireDot.
Changes to properties files to work with container independent setup script.
Change from log4j to slf4j with logback
Corrected the "Study" entity to avoid NullPointer exceptions
Fixed a resource leak in lucene populate
Lucene populate is now much faster. This is mainly because it uses multiple threads
It is recommended to avoid this version of ICAT if you are using multiple icat servers as testing of such configurations has not been carried out.

4.5.1

Fix bug where ICAT won't start up with an empty lucene index

4.5.0

Remove lucene calls and apply bug fixes.

Permit lucene not to be used by omitting references in icat.setup.
All lucene calls have been commented out - they will be reinstated in 4.6 but they will be different.
Allow queries of the form "SELECT a.b.c FROM ..." This was not documented but used to work in ICAT 4.3 and is standard JPQL.
Provide better protection against queries that are getting too large a quantity of data back from the database. Previously the "maxEntities" check was only made at the time when the XML response to the user was generated by which time it could have been too late. A side effect of this is that in some cases when an aggregate function is part of a query which would of course only return one record this may now fail if the data being aggregated are very large. Even if such queries are handled by the database, SUM and AVG are potentially very slow as they cannot benefit from any indexing.
Fixed the ordering of entities appearing in the output file when using exportData in the restful API so that the file can be re-imported.
Instead of doubled up '"' characters use '\"' and also introduce \b \t \n \f \r \\ and the not strictly necessary \' for the import export format.
Avoid the use of a sequence table for allocating IDs. It should be noted that a side effect of this is that for MySQL there is no longer a global ID sequence but the ID sequences are specific to a table.
LIMIT clause in the query now works properly when searching by id. This requires a manual schema upgrade if you already have an ICAT installed.
Ensure that createTime and endTime are represented by ISO 8601 style json strings like other TIMESTAMP fields using the RESTful search call.
Provide protection against an EclipseLink bug with Oracle which resulted in BigDecimal objects being returned instead of Long or Double values when MIN or MAX of a value of that type was requested.
The documentation for the rootUserNames parameter has been updated to match a change introduced in release 4.4 whereby users listed in rootUserNames have full access to all tables.
json returned by restful calls now encodes numbers and booleans correctly.
The restful calls now produce CORS headers.

4.4.0

This introduces a number of "RESTful" calls and has some other small improvements and bug fixes.

A bug in the authorization computation has been fixed which was previously prohibiting operations that should have been allowed in some cases where multiple authorization rules were relevant.
A partial prototype of a "RESTful" interface has been added.
There is a new parameter maxEntities which must be specified in icat.properties to restrict the total number of entities returned in calls to get, search and searchText.
There is a new parameter maxIdsInQuery which must be specified in icat.properties to restrict the size of ICAT generated queries. This must not exceed 1000 if Oracle is being used.
There are new parameters importCacheSize and exportCacheSize which must be specified in icat.properties to restrict the size of caches used during import and export. The cache is local to a call to import or export to ensure that authorization rules are enforced. As a by-product modifications to ICAT are less likely to result in stale information being returned from the cache.
ID values are obtained from the database SEQUENCE table in groups of 500 rather than 50 to improve performance. This is to circumvent a problem seen occasionally in Oracle.
The DISTINCT keyword now works as in regular JPQL.
Queries are now truncated to 4000 characters before storing them in the table or file log.
The installation script has been made more robust and will also ensure that JDBC connectors are set up in a resilient manner for Oracle RAC servers.
It is now treated as an error to have redundant paths in an INCLUDE clause.
The application is now built and deployed as a .war files rather than a .ear file which makes it easier to deploy on Wildfly.
The InvestigationGroup has been introduced. It is expected that this will be generally used in Rule based authorization in preference to InvestigationUser except for those cases where the role of the individual is significant.
The role field in the InvestigationUser is now part of the key and can now not be null. This allows a User to have multiple roles relative to an Investigation
The Rule.what column has been increased in length from the default of 255 to 1024.

4.3.3

This is a bug fix release with support for a group of ICATs working together. It is not a cluster in the Glassfish sense.

The isAccessAllowed call, when used to check CREATE access, is now protected from invalid input.
All standard JPQL functions are now accepted in search() calls.
Queries returning results of aggregate functions should always return an array of length 1. However, due to the behaviour of JAXB a list containing just a null is not transmitted properly and instead an empty list is returned. This is a problem with the functions MIN, MAX, SUM and AVG all of which return null when they have no data to process. The COUNT function was also returning an empty list when it had no data but now returns a list containing 0L.
More than one ICAT may be used together to share the load and provide more resilience.
The setup script does not require calling with the configure option.
The icat-setup.properties file now uses the keyword dbProperties rather than icatProperties.
Fixed bug with handling of unary minus.

4.3.2

This is a bug fix release.

A get call using the old (non-JPQL) syntax will now accept the INCLUDE keyword in lower or mixed case.

4.3.1

This is a bug fix release.

The methods logout and refresh when called with an expired or otherwise invalid sessionId now throw an exception of type SESSION rather than INTERNAL.
A small improvement to testicat has been made to show who you are logged in as.
The relationship from DataCollection to DataCollectionParameters is now called parameters and can be accessed by getParameters and setParameters.

4.3.0

This includes schema changes and a number of speculative features.

The "ICATCompat" service for backwards compatibility with ICAT 3.x has now been removed.
A method "void refresh(String sid)" has been added to refresh an ICAT session.
The notification mechanism has been completely changed.
It is not legal in queries with an INCLUDE to use a "1" in conjunction with and entity name. This will now reliably throw an exception.
A new call "boolean isAccessAllowed" has been created to test whether a specific access type is allowed.
A call has been provided to return all the available entity names. This is of more use to tools than regular users.
Column names in the Database table for UserGroup have been changed as they were inconsistent.
The Rule entities are now store in a database table called RULE_. for compatibility with Microsoft SQLServer.
A file indices.sql is being distributed with the .ear file with indices which may improve performance. You should assess whether or not each index will be useful to your installation for while an index can give a huge improvement to a query there is also a cost in maintaining an index.
JPA mappings for floating point numbers now use precision 38 and scale 19. This is still not good on Oracle as mentioned in the installation instructions.
testicat.py (which replaces test.py) expects https://hostname:port rather than a pair of parameters
Call logging has been added either to file or to a log table or both.
Lucene free text search has been included via the new searchText call.
Changed uniqueness constraints to:

Datafile
dataset, name (-location)
Dataset
investigation, name (-sample -type)
Application
facility, name, version (+facility)
Sample
investigation, name (-type)
Investigation
facility, name, visitid (-facilityCycle -instrument)
SampleType
facility, name, molecularFormula (+molecularFormula)

Made all constraint fields not nullable. This is checked by ICAT to ensure that future changes do not break this rule.
Add a string attribute: "arguments" to the job to store the program arguments that were used.
Relationship between FacilityCycle and Investigation removed.
Table between Investigation and Instrument added to represent many-to-many relationships between them.
Added DataCollection and changed Job to make use if it.
Group has been changed to Grouping as Group is a JPQL keyword.
Add attribute 'url' to Instrument.
Added new alternate query syntax that may be used in queries and authz rules. It is distinguished by starting with the keyword "SELECT".
It is no longer considered an error to have no authz rules matching a search call - you just get no data back.
Packaging now conforms to http://code.google.com/p/icatproject/wiki/ComponentGuidelines
A command icatadmin has been introduced to perform operations for which the rule based authorization is not appropriate.
Expired sessions are cleaned out of the database every hour.
The generated client jar contains two packages: org.icatproject and org.icatproject_4_3_0. Normal users should use the org.icatproject one. The other exists primarily for TopCAT so that multiple ICAT clients can co-exist.
The installation mechanism now has a single setup Python script which works both on Linux and Windows.

4.2.5

This is a bug fix release. If you already have 4.2.0, 4.2.1, 4.2.2, 4.2.3 or 4.2.4 installed, then simply remove the old ear file and deploy the new one. If you have changed log4j.properties from the one supplied then add an entry to your icat.properties: log4j.properties = log4j.properties which tells the ICAT to use the existing log4j.properties file in the config directory rather than the built in one. If you have not changed it then it is preferable to delete the log4j.properties from the config directory to avoid any possible confusion. The log4j.properties file is no longer reread, if you have configured your own copy and wish to change it then you must at least reload ICAT for the properties file to be read again.

A significant leak has been fixed which was causing an unlimited number of threads to be created. This has been addressed by changing the way in which the log4j.properties file is read. Only if you have a line in the icat.properties identifying a specific log4j.properties file will that file be used, otherwise a default file packaged within the .ear file will be used.

4.2.4

This is a bug fix release. If you already have 4.2.0, 4.2.1, 4.2.2 or 4.2.3 installed, then simply remove the old ear file and deploy the new one.

Version number updated to 4.2.4 and test updated to ensure that the version corresponds to the maven project version.
LICENSE.txt file added to top directory of the source tree.
Creating an Investigation which refers to a new InvestigationUser now works properly.
Using INCLUDE with User and Group now works properly. Previously it could throw a null pointer exception.
Database requirements have been made more precise in the deployment instructions.

4.2.3

This is a bug fix release. If you already have 4.2.0, 4.2.1 or 4.2.2 installed, then simply remove the old ear file and deploy the new one.

Two different error conditions were not being handled correctly in calls to createMany when a user attempted to violate a uniqueness constraint. In the case of a conflict with a pre-existing entry in ICAT the offset returned was -1. In the case that there were duplicates in the list passed in the call to createMany - rather than conflicts with existing database entries - an IcatException of type INTERNAL was being thrown, also with an offset of -1. These bugs are now fixed.

4.2.2

This is a bug fix release. If you already have 4.2.0 or 4.2.1 installed, then simply remove the old ear file and deploy the new one.

A bug causing read access to be denied in certain circumstances, when it should have been permitted, has been fixed.
When attempting to format an error message about an invalid list of INCLUDES a null pointer exception is no longer thrown.

4.2.1

This is a bug fix release. If you already have 4.2.0 installed, then simply remove the old ear file and deploy the new one.

Authorization rules without explicit relationships to groups (of the form "Investigation <-> InvestigationUser <-> User [name = :user]") now work properly.
It is now possible to use boolean values in queries. Attributes can be compared against literal values of TRUE and FALSE (not case sensitive) as in "ParameterType [enforced = TRUE]"
Null pointer exceptions were being throw with some authorization rules when using an Oracle database. This has now been fixed.

4.2.0

This introduces a clean mechanism for handling authentication plugins and provides significant speed enhancements.

ICAT now contains no authentication plugins but it does provide an Authenticator interface for plugin writers. If you plan to use the new authn_db database authentication plugin you will need to manually move data from the old table to the new passwd table.
The login call now accepts two parameters, the mnemonic for the authentication plugin and a map of credentials. This change necessitated the increase in the version number to 4.2.
There was a serious performance bug in release 4.1 and to a lesser extent in 4.0. In both case this affected read operations - search and get. This bug in the marshalling of the XML has now been addressed.
Previously JMS messages had the property "query" set to the primary key and the actual query value was not available. They are now assigned correctly to the properties "query" and "entityId".
You will need an up-to-date version of JAX-WS such as the one packaged with Glassfish 3.1.2
The main database schema is almost unchanged. The only difference is that some text fields have been made larger.
A bug has been fixed in the handling of enum types in expressions.

4.1.1

This is a bug fix release.

Aggregate functions (MIN, MAX, AVG, COUNT etc) no longer generate an internal exception.
Minor improvements to the installation documentation.

4.1.0

This is the first release of ICAT4 which is meant to be approaching production quality.

More changes to the API - too numerous to list here providing

support for pluggable authn,
support for rule based authz,
support for notifications and
a powerful search mechanism

Database independent
More regular schema with simple provenance mechanism

4.0.0

Technology preview release - not for production use

Many changes to the API

3.3.4

Changed the JPA provider from TopLink to EclipseLink
Removed Dataportal from the installation

3.3.3

Public release

ICAT SOAP Manual

Contents

Conventions
Setting up
Session management
Exceptions
Data Manipulation

Creating an Object
Retrieving an object when you know its id
Updating an Object
Deleting an Object
Searching for an Object

Authorization

Rules
Checking accessibility
PublicStep

System Information
Administration Calls
Concise Syntax

Conventions

In order to document the behaviour of the web service it is generally described in terms of calls on a Java client. Most examples are in Java but with a few Python equivalents where it is sufficiently different.

Setting up

The web service is accessed via a proxy (conventionally known in Java as a port). The proxy (here given a variable name of icat) may be obtained by the following:

URL hostUrl = new URL("https://<hostname>:8181")
URL icatUrl = new URL(hostUrl, "ICATService/ICAT?wsdl");
QName qName = new QName("http://icatproject.org", "ICATService");
ICATService service = new ICATService(icatUrl, qName);
ICAT icat = service.getICATPort();

where <hostname> should be the full name of the ICAT server. For a secure installation, just specifying localhost will not work, the name must match what is on the host certificate.

The corresponding Python suds code is:

from suds.client import Client
client = Client(url)
icat = client.service
factory = client.factory

methods may then be invoked on the icat object and entities created using the factory.

Session management

When you login to ICAT you will be given back a string, the sessionId, which must be used as the first argument of almost all ICAT calls. The only exceptions being the login call itself, getEntityInfo and getApiVersion - none of which require authentication.

String login(String plugin, Credentials credentials)

where the plugin is the mnemonic defined in the ICAT installation for the authentication plugin you wish to use and credentials is essentially a map. The names of the keys and their meaning is defined by the plugin.

This sessionId returned will be valid for a period determined by the ICAT server.

The example below shows how it works for the authn_db plugin at the time of writing, where the plugin has been given the mnemonic "db".

Credentials credentials = new Credentials();
List<Entry> entries = credentials.getEntry();
Entry e;

e = new Entry();
e.setKey("username");
e.setValue("root");
entries.add(e);
e = new Entry();
e.setKey("password");
e.setValue("secret");
entries.add(e);

String sessionId = icat.login("db", credentials);

The corresponding Python code, using the factory and icat service defined above is:

credentials = factory.create("login.credentials")

entry = factory.create("login.credentials.entry")
entry.key = "username"
entry.value = "root"
credentials.entry.append(entry)
entry = factory.create("login.credentials.entry")
entry.key = "password"
entry.value = "secret"
credentials.entry.append(entry)

sessionId = icat.login("db", credentials)

double getRemainingMinutes(String sessionId)

This returns the number of minutes left in the session. A user may have more than one session at once.

String getUserName(String sessionId)

This returns the string identifying the user of the session as provided by the authentication plugin.

void refresh(String sessionId)

This resets the time-to-live of the session as it was when the session was first obtained.

void logout(String sessionId)

This invalidates the sessionId.

Exceptions

There is only one exception thrown by ICAT. In the case of Java this is the IcatException_Exception which is a wrapper around the real exception which in turn includes an enumerated code to identify the kind of exception and the usual message. The codes and their meanings are:

BAD_PARAMETER
generally indicates a problem with the arguments made to a call.
INTERNAL
may be caused by network problems, database problems, glassfish problems or bugs in ICAT.
INSUFFICIENT_PRIVILEGES
indicates that the authorization rules have not matched your request.
NO_SUCH_OBJECT_FOUND
is thrown when something is not found.
OBJECT_ALREADY_EXISTS
is thrown when type to create something but there is already one with the same values of the constraint fields.
SESSION
is used when the sessionId you have passed into a call is not valid or if you are unable to authenticate.
VALIDATION
marks an exception which was thrown instead of placing the database in an invalid state.

For example to print what has happened you might use the following (in Java):

String sessionId;
try {
    sessionId = icat.login("db", credentials);
} catch (IcatException_Exception e) {
    IcatException ue = e.getFaultInfo();
    System.out.println("IcatException " + ue.getType() + " " + ue.getMessage()
    + (ue.getOffset() >= 0 ? " at offset " + ue.getOffset() : ""));
}

The corresponding Python code looks like:

try:
    sessionId = icat.login("db", credentials)
except WebFault as e:
    etype = e.fault.detail.IcatException.type
    message = e.fault.detail.IcatException.message
    offset = e.fault.detail.IcatException.offset
    print "IcatException " + etype + " " + message + (" at offset " + offset) if offset >= 0 else ""

Operations which work on a list of objects, such as createMany, may fail because of failure to process one of the objects. In this case the state of the database will be rolled back and the offset within the list of the entry causing the error will be stored in the IcatException. For other calls the offset will be negative, as it is with certain internal exceptions which are not associated with any specific object in a list.

Data Manipulation

Creating an Object

long create(String sessionId, EntityBaseBean bean)

To create an object in ICAT, first instantiate the object of interest, for example a Dataset, and then call the setters to set its attributes and finally make a call to create the object in ICAT.

So typical code in Java might look like:

Dataset ds = new Dataset();
ds.setName("Name of dataset");
ds.set ...
Long dsid = icat.create(sessionId, ds);

You will see that no convenient constructors are generated, rather each field of the object must be set individually.

The corresponding code in Python is shownn below. Note that the factory.create takes the lower case name "dataset" rather than "Dataset"

ds = factory.create("dataset")
ds.name = "Name of dataset"
ds. ...
dsid = icat.create(sessionId, ds);

Most fields are optional and may be left with null values, however some are compulsory and the call to create will fail if they are not set. Each object has a primary key that identifies it in the database - this is a value of type "long" that is generated by ICAT and is used to represent relationships in a regular manner.

Some fields represent attributes of the object but others are used to represent relationships. The relationships are represented in the class definitions by a variable which either holds a reference to a single object or a list of objects. In the case of a list it may be "cascaded". Consider creating a dataset with a set of datafiles. Because the relationship from dataset to datafile is cascaded they may be created in one call as outlined by the Java code below:

Dataset ds = new Dataset();
ds.setName(dsName);
ds.setType(type);
Datafile datafile = new Datafile();
datafile.setDatafileFormat(format);
datafile.setName(dfName);
ds.getDatafiles().add(datafile); // Add the datafile to the dataset
icat.create(sessionId, ds);

The call to create returns the key of the created object. If you choose to write the Java code

ds.setId(icat.create(sessionId, ds));

then the client copy of the Dataset will be updated to have the correct key value - however the keys in any other objects "within" the Dataset will still be null on the client side. In this case datafile.getId() will remain null.

It might help to understand what is happening when you call create. The client side object you pass in, and everything it refers to , is encoded as XML and sent to the server. There it is unpacked into the same set of objects and persisted in the database. The structure passed in must be a tree structure (or more correctly a DAG ) - if, for example, you modify the code above to create a dataset with one datafile and add datafile.setDataset(dataset) attempting to put in a reverse link which physically will appear in the ICAT database the call will be rejected by the client because you have a loop in the graph as you can then go backwards and forwards between datafile and dataset. If you passed in a proper DAG the database will create one row in the dataset table and one in the datafile table where the datafile entry includes the field datafile.dataset_id holding the dataset.id of the dataset entry just created. Relationships are represented in the database by holding the id value of the related object.

We now have a Java example of adding a datafile to an existing dataset, ds

Datafile datafile = new Datafile();
datafile.setDatafileFormat(format);
datafile.setName(name);
datafile.setDataset(ds); // Relate the datafile to an existing dataset
datafile.setId(icat.create(sessionId, datafile)); // Create datafile and store id on client side

This is the only way to create a datafile and add it to a dataset - you cannot do it by any operation upon the dataset. A datafile cannot be created without a dataset. After the call is made a new entry will have been been added to the datafile table in the database where again the field datafile.dataset_id in the database will have been set to the dataset.id of the related dataset which in this case may be more intuitive as it corresponds to the line of user code datafile.setDataset(ds) .

It is worth noting that the dataset object you have in memory is not affected by the call to create a new datafile. More datafiles can be created referencing the same dataset without retrieving an updated copy of the dataset.

List <Long> createMany(String sessionId, List <EntityBaseBean> beans)

This call, as its name suggests, creates many objects. It takes the list of objects to create and returns a list of ids. If any of the individual operations fail the whole call fails and the database will be unchanged. The objects to be created need not be of the same type. For an example (where they are of the same type) consider adding many Datafiles to a existing Dataset, ds in Java:

List <Datafile> dfs = new ArrayList<Datafile>();
for (int i = 0; i < n; i++) {
    Datafile datafile = new Datafile();
    datafile.setDatafileFormat(dfmt);
    datafile.setName("bill" + i);
    datafile.setDataset(ds);
    dfs.add(datafile);
}
icat.createMany(sesionId, dfs); // many datafiles are stored in one call

The equivalent Python code is:

dfs = []
for i in range(n):
    datafile = factory.create("datafile")
    datafile.datafileFormat = dfmt)
    datafile.name = "bill" + str(i)
    datafile.dataset = ds
    dfs.append(datafile)
icat.createMany(sesionId, dfs)

The only reason that this call exists is to minimize calls to ICAT as it is faster to call createMany than to make many calls to create .

Retrieving an object when you know its id

EntityBaseBean get(String sessionId, String query, long id)

The first parameter is the sessionId, the second is a query string which in the simplest case is just the name of the type of object and the last parameter is the id of the object. You may know the id of an object because you have created it or it was returned from a search call. For example in Java:

get(sessionId, "Dataset", 75L)

will return the Dataset with an id of 75 or throw an exception if it is not found. The dataset is returned on its own with no related objects; the set of related datafiles will be empty and the type (which is a related object) will be null. Often however you will want to return related objects as well. To get a Dataset with all its Datafiles you can use the query:

Dataset ds INCLUDE ds.datafiles

This uses the variable "ds" to identify the selected dataset. The Dataset field "datafiles" will be followed to include all those "Datafiles" related to the selected dataset. Those datafiles which the user is not allowed to read are silently ignored.

To get a Dataset with all its Datafiles, DatasetParameters and DatafileParameters you can use the query:

Dataset ds INCLUDE ds.datafiles df, df.parameters, ds.parameters

which has introduced another variable df to represent the set of (readable) datafiles and which are related to the initial dataset ds. The variable could be preceded by the keyword "AS" if you feel this makes it easier to read as in:

Dataset ds INCLUDE ds.datafiles AS df, df.parameters, ds.parameters

To save typing you could write the equivalent:

Dataset ds INCLUDE ds.datafiles.parameters, ds.parameters

This slightly shortened form may make it less obvious that the datafiles are also included in the set of returned objects. In fact they must be present as the returned objects always form a DAG again and the DatafileParameters need the Datafiles to connect in to the structure.

It is permissible to visit an entity type more than once in an INCLUDE - for example following a provenance chain or including the datasets with the same type as a particular dataset which would be:

Dataset ds INCLUDE ds.type t, t.datasets

There is also a special notation "INCLUDE 1" which is described in the next section.

Updating an Object

void update(String sessionId, EntityBaseBean bean)

To update an object simply retrieve it, update the fields you want to change and call update. For example to change the name of the dataset to "Fred":

Dataset ds = (Dataset) icat.get(sessionId, "Dataset INCLUDE 1", dsid);
ds.setName("Fred");
icat.update(sessionId, ds);

All "many to one" relationships, such as the relationship to the Investigation, will be updated as will any simple field values. Consequently it is essential to get the existing values for any "many to one" relationships otherwise they will be set to null. This is most reliably achieved by the notation INCLUDE 1 as shown here. The effect of the "1" is to include all "many to one" related types. "One to many" relationships, such as the set of Datafiles are ignored by the update mechanism. If your attempted change violates a uniqeness constraint an exception will be thrown.

In addition "many to one" relationships can be modified. For example to make the Dataset part of a different Investigation:

Dataset ds = (Dataset) icat.get(sessionId, "Dataset INCLUDE 1", dsid);
ds.setInvestigation(anotherInvestigation);
icat.update(sessionId, ds);

The equivalent Python code is:

ds = icat.get(sessionId, "Dataset INCLUDE 1", dsid)
ds.investigation = anotherInvestigation
icat.update(sessionId, ds);

It is sufficient for the relation object to just have the id value correct as the rest of the fields are ignored. For example if you know the id of the Investigation then you could write in Python:

ds = icat.get(sessionId, "Dataset INCLUDE 1", dsid)
inv = factory.create("investigation")
inv.id = anotherInvestigationId
ds.investigation = inv
icat.update(sessionId, ds);

Deleting an Object

void delete(String sessionId, EntityBaseBean bean)

The following Java code will get a dataset and delete it.

Dataset ds = (Dataset) icat.get(sessionId, "Dataset", dsid);
icat.delete(sessionId, ds);

All "one to many" related objects will also be deleted. In the extreme case, if you delete a facility, you lose everything associated with that facility. This privilege should not be given to many - see the authorization section later. When you get a local copy of the object to delete there is no need to use INCLUDE 1 to populate the "one to many" related objects as all cascades will be followed. In fact the only part of the object that is used by the delete call is the id. So the following Java code will have the same effect and avoids one ICAT call:

Dataset ds = new Dataset()
ds.setId(dsid);
icat.delete(sessionId, ds);

Searching for an Object

The syntax is a standard JPQL "SELECT" statement with with two extensions a LIMIT clause and an INCLUDE clause which may come in either order after the standard JPQL. The only restriction is that returned item must be a set of entities, the result of an aggregate function (such as COUNT or MAX) or a set of values of one field of an entity type. If you use nested selects please define new variable names for use within such a construct. Some keywords, such as FETCH, are not relevant and are ignored. The language, which borrows a lot from SQL is well explained in the Oracle JPQL documentation.

There are also two extensions to JPQL a LIMIT clause and an INCLUDE clause which may come in either order after the standard JPQL. The LIMIT clase follows MySQL syntax and takes the form: LIMIT 10, 100 which will skip 10 results and return the next 100. A LIMIT clause will normally be used with an ORDER BY clause. The INCLUDE clause is just as as has been explained for the get call . A few examples are shown below:

SELECT ds FROM Dataset ds INCLUDE ds.datafiles.parameters, ds.parameters

This uses the variable "ds" defined in the FROM clause. It means that the "Dataset" field "datafiles" will be followed to include all those "Datafiles" and that for each "Datafile" the "parameters" field will be followed to get the "DatafileParameters". In addition the "DatasetParameters" will be included. A more interesting example is:

SELECT ds.name FROM Dataset ds WHERE ds.type.name = 'GS' ORDER BY ds.name LIMIT 0, 10"

This will take the first 10 datasets (as ordered by name) which have a type with a name of 'GS'. The next example is looking for the ids of datasets which have both a parameter A1 > 50 and a parameter A2 > 20

SELECT ds.id FROM Dataset ds, ds.parameters dp1, ds.parameters dp2 WHERE
dp1.type.name = 'A1' AND dp1.numericValue > 50 AND
dp2.type.name = 'A2' AND dp2.numericValue > 20

Note in the example above how the parameters dp1 and dp2 were introduced. The form :user may be used to denote the currently authenticated user (derived from the sessionId). For example to see the investigations to which you are associated:

SELECT i FROM Investigation i, i.investigationUsers ius WHERE ius.user.name = :user

Time literals (which are implementation dependent in JPQL) should be expressed as shown in the next example:

SELECT i FROM Investigation i WHERE i.createTime > {ts 2011-01-15 00:00:00}

The timestamp format must be exactly as shown. Literal boolean values are TRUE and FALSE as in:

SELECT ds FROM Dataset ds WHERE ds.complete = TRUE

and finally enums are expressed as shown below:

SELECT pt FROM ParameterType pt WHERE pt.valueType = org.icatproject.ParameterValueType.DATE_AND_TIME

which is selecting those ParameterTypes which have a valueType of ParameterValueType.DATE_AND_TIME. Note that the full class name org.icatproject.ParameterValueType must be specified.

Joins can be performed - for example

SELECT u FROM User u JOIN u.userGroups ug JOIN ug.grouping g WHERE g.name='FacilityAdmins'

Authorization

The mechanism is rule based. Rules allow groupings of users to do things. There are four things that can be done: Create, Read, Update and Delete. It makes use of five entity types: Rule, User, Grouping, UserGroup and PublicStep. The name "Grouping" has been introduced as, the more natural, "Group" is a reserved word in JPQL. The authentication mechanism authenticates a person with a certain name and this name identifies the User in the ICAT User table. Groupings have names and the UserGroup performs the function of a "many to many" relationship between Users and Groupings. Rules are applied to Groupings. There are special "root users" with full access to all entities. The set of "root users" is a configuration parameter of the ICAT installation. Only a root user can set up the initial set of authorization rules though these rules can then allow others to manipulate rules.

Though the authorization rules are handled as efficiently as possible to get the best performance define a rule to make those entity types world readable where this makes sense. Such rules have no conditions in the "what" field and the grouping field is left null. Such rules are recognised and are cached in memory. Typically those entities which are used to implement a many to many relationship can be world readable as can those which represent types. The PublicStep mechanism is also available to cover the case where access to one entity implies that another may be accessed. For example you might define a PublicStep from Datafile to its Dataset (via the dataset field) and from a Dataset to its Investigation (via the investigation field). For other cases you will need to write rules.

Rules

By default access is denied to all objects, rules allow access. It is only necessary to be permitted by one rule where that rule is only applied to the object referenced directly in the API call. The Rule table has two exposed fields: crudFlags and what . The field crudFlags contains letters from the set "CRUD" to indicate which types of operation are being allowed (Create, Read, Update and/or Delete). The other field, what , is the rule itself. There is also a "many to one" relationship to Grouping which may be absent.

Consider the Java code:

Rule rule = new Rule();
rule.setGrouping(userOffice);
rule.setCrudFlags("CRUD");
rule.setWhat("Investigation");
icat.create(sessionId, rule);

allows members of the userOffice Grouping full access to all Investigations.

Rule rule = new Rule();
rule.setGrouping(null); // Not necessary as it will be null on a newly created rule
rule.setCrudFlags("R");
rule.setWhat("ParameterType");
icat.create(sessionId, rule);

allows any authenticated user (with a sessionId) to read Parameters. Consider a Grouping of users: fredReaders. To allow fredReaders to read a datafile with a name of "fred" we could have:

Rule rule = new Rule();
rule.setGrouping(fredReaders);
rule.setCrudFlags("R");
rule.setWhat("SELECT Datafile df WHERE df.name='fred'");
icat.create(sessionId, rule);

The what field may contain almost anything which may appear as a search query. The query, if evaluated, would return the set of objects which can be read, updated or deleted in the case of R, U and D crudFlags. For the C crudFlag which controls create operations, the call is allowed if after creation of the object it would be in the set defined by the what field. Control of update operations is more complex if the update includes modification of any field that identifies the object. In this case the user must have delete access to the object before the change and create access after the change.

To control access to the complete object the search query in the what field must return a set of objects rather than a set of fields or an aggregate function. The query must not contain INCLUDE, LIMIT nor ORDER BY clauses.

More complex restrictions can be added using other related objects. For example to allow read access to Datasets belonging to an Investigation which includes an InvestigationUser which has a user with a name matching the currently authenticated user (from the sessionId) we can have:

Rule rule = new Rule();
rule.setGrouping(null);
rule.setCrudFlags("R");
rule.setWhat("select Dataset ds, ds.investigation i, i.investigationUser iu WHERE iu.name = :user");
icat.create(sessionId, rule);

The rules shown so far permit access to all the fields of the object. However for READ and UPDATE it makes sense to control access to an individual attribute. To express this a rule may reference a specific attribute. For example the following Python:

rule = factory.create("rule")
rule.crudFlags = "U" rule.grouping = invHackers rule.what = "select Investigation inv.doi" icat.create(sessionId, rule)

allows members of the invHackers grouping to modify the doi field of all Investigations. Currently only the UPDATE operation can be controlled this way. It would be possible to also support READ however as yet no compelling Use Case has been encountered.

Rules which allow everyone to read a table are cached in memory and are good for performance. For example to give universal read access to DatasetType the following Java code could be used:

Rule rule = new Rule();
rule.setGrouping(null);
rule.setCrudFlags("R");
rule.setWhat("DatasetType");
icat.create(sessionId, rule);

PublicStep

This table has two columns (origin and field). An entry in this table affects the way in which INCLUDE authorization is carried out. Each entry permits all users to make a step from the origin entity by the specified relationship field without any further checking. This information is held in memory for speed. For those INCLUDEs that are not mentioned in the PublicStep table a full read authorization check must be made before including an object to be returned - which can be expensive. The following Python code permits the jobs relationship to be followed from an Application.

ps = factory.create("publicStep)
ps.origin = "Application"
ps.field = "jobs"
session.create(ps)

This will mean that if you have a query "SELECT Application a INCLUDE a.jobs" then the system will only return applications your are authorized to read. It will also provide all the jobs which are related to those applications provided you are authorized to do so. In the absence of a PublicStep it will check each one individually which can be time consuming but with this PublicStep in place the system will simply following the relationship without further checks.

Checking accessibility

boolean isAccessAllowed(String sessionId, EntityBaseBean bean, AccessType accessType)

This call returns true if the access to the bean specified by the accessType is permitted. For example:

Dataset ds = new Dataset();
ds.setName("Name of dataset");
ds.set ...
System.out.println(isAccessAllowed(sessionId, ds, AccessType.CREATE))

This code sets up a Dataset and then prints whether or not it would be allowed to create it.

This call is expected to be made from GUIs so that they can avoid offering operations that will fail. As such, though READ acess may be queried it is unlikely to be useful as the GUI user will not have found out about the object to be checked. If READ, DELETE or UPDATE access is queried for an object that does not exist it will return false.

In the case of CREATE, the entity is created within a database transaction, the check is made and the transaction is rolled back. Note that if a create operation would result in a duplicate this will cause an exception to be thrown.

System Information

String getApiVersion()

returns the version of the server

List<String> getEntityNames()

Returns an alphabetic list of all the entity names known to ICAT. This is of most value for tools.

EntityInfo getEntityInfo(String beanName)

returns full information about a table given its name. For example:

EntityInfo ei = icat.getEntityInfo("Investigation");
System.out.println(ei.getClassComment());
for (Constraint c : ei.getConstraints()) {
  ;  ;  ;System.out.println("Constraint columns: " + c.getFieldNames());
}
for (EntityField f : ei.getFields()) {
  ;  ;  ;System.out.println("Field names: " + f.getName());
}

Prints out some information about the Investigation table. For a list of all available fields in EntityInfo and the objects it references please consult the javadoc for EntityInfo .

Administration Calls

To be authorized to use administration calls you must be authenticated with a name listed in the rootUserNames in the run.properties file.

List<String> getProperties(String sessionId)

lists the active contents of the run.properties file. It does this by examining the properties after they have been read in so any superfluous definitions in the original properties file will not be seen. The current physical file is not re-examined

Concise Syntax

Originally ICAT did not support JPQL but instead had its own concise query syntax. The concise syntax however is not as general as JPQL and so cannot express some queries. At some time in the future support for the concise syntax may be removed - you have been warned.

If the query is simply Dataset this will return all Datasets. If the query is Dataset.name this will return all Dataset names. To get related objects returned, then use INCLUDE followed by a list of object types:

Dataset INCLUDE Datafile,DatasetParameter,DatafileParameter

The related types must be all be related to the original type or to some other type in the list. This means that you could not have "Dataset INCLUDE DatafileParameter" . In addition there must be only one route from the original type to each of the included types - i.e. you can only construct one DAG from the starting object.

You can specify an order (which may precede or follow an INCLUDE clause):

Dataset.id ORDER BY id

Restrictions can be placed on the data returned. For example:

Dataset.id [type.name IN ('GS', 'GQ')]

which could also be written:

Dataset.id [type.name = 'GS' OR type.name = 'GQ']

The restriction in the square brackets can be as complex as required - but must only refer to attributes of the object being restricted - in this case the Dataset. Expressions may use parentheses, AND, OR, <, <=, >, >=, =, <>, !=, NOT, IN, LIKE and BETWEEN. Currently the BETWEEN operator does not work on strings. This appears to be a JPA bug.

Functions: MAX, MIN, COUNT, AVG and SUM may also be used such as:

MAX (Dataset.id)

Selection may involve more than one related object. To show the relationship a "<->" token is used. For example:

Dataset.id <-> DatasetParameter[type.name = 'TIMESTAMP']

Note also here the use of the JPQL style path: type.name . This expressions means ids of Datasets which have a DatasetParameter which has a type with a name of TIMESTAMP. Multiple " <->" may appear but all the objects involved, including the first one, must be connectable in only one way . The next example show how restrictions may be applied to both the Dataset and the DatasetParameter:

Dataset.id [name like 'fred%'] <-> DatasetParameter[type.name = 'TIMESTAMP']

It is also possible to restrict the number of results returned by specifying a pair of numbers at the beginning of the query string. This construct would normally be used with an ORDER BY clause. The first number is the offset from within the full list of available results from which to start returning data and the second is the maximum number of results to return. These numbers if specified must be positive. If the offset is greater than or equal to the number of internal results then no data will be returned. The default values are 0 and "infinity". The numbers must be separated by a comma though either may be omitted. The following are all valid:

3,5 Dataset.id ORDER BY id
3, Dataset.id ORDER BY id
,5 Dataset.id ORDER BY id

To see the investigations to which you are associated you can make use of the special value :user as in:

Investigation <-> InvestigationUser [name = :user]

Time literals (which are implementation dependent in JPQL) should be expressed as shown in the next example:

Investigation [createTime > {ts 2011-01-15 00:00:00}]

The timestamp format must be exactly as shown. Literal boolean values are TRUE and FALSE as in:

Dataset [complete = TRUE]

and finally enums are expressed as shown below:

ParameterType [valueType = DATE_AND_TIME]

which is selecting those ParameterTypes which have a valueType of DATE_AND_TIME from ParameterTypeValue.

Introduction

The ICAT server is a layer on top of a relational DBMS. The database is wrapped both as a SOAP web service and as a RESTful web service.

SOAP interface

For the SOAP web service each table in the database is mapped onto a data structure exposed by the web service. When the web service interface definition (WSDL) is processed by a client then it has sufficient information to allow an object to be built on the client side matching rows of each table in the database. The convenience of using the SOAP interface depends critically upon the level of support provided by the libraries available.

In Java support is good and tools such as wsimport can be used to generate client stubs to make it very easy to use and to provide type safety. Java client libraries have been - see icat.client.

In the case of Python, Suds (or preferably the jurko fork of suds) can be used. This uses the wsdl to allow factory methods to create the objects in the python client corresponding to the rows of the database tables. In addition there is the python-icat library which s a Python package that provides a collection of modules for writing programs that access an ICAT service using the SOAP interface. It is based on Suds and extends it with ICAT specific features and also provides a level of protection from server version dependency.

SOAP is basically RPC and the client must match the server. The protocol is XML based and so is rather verbose and because you can only transfer predefined objects you cannot issue a query which returns a projection of a join as you would expect to be able to do in an RDBMS. This means that more data are transferred than needed. This means that you cannot get back a table of Facility names and Investigation names for all investigations with a DOI attached. Instead you would have to get all the matching Investigations along with the the related Facility. Not only would you get back all the columns of the Investigation and Facility tables that you don't want but all the Facility information would typically be sent many times - each time it is referenced by an Investigation. In addition the WSDL (though generated automatically from the Java code of the server) contains no code derived documentation.

RESTful interface

This service acts upon HTTP methods (GET, PUT, DELETE etc.) and processes JSON input and returns JSON. The client programmer gets no help in producing these JSON messages to represent sets of database rows to send to the server nor in dealing with the JSON which is returned. Some help is provided by the rest part of the icat.client with those calls that don't pass sets of entities around. Otherwise for manipulating JSON from Java the javax.json package is recommended and from Python the json package is recommended. The javax.json package provides streaming and non-streaming libraries and the Python json library allows for conversion between JSON and Python object trees made up of lists and dictionaries.

Session Management

The icat server is configured with a number of authenticator plugins. To login to a server requires that you identify the plugin and pass it suitable credentials. These credentials are sent as key value pairs. Mostly the keywords are username and password but this is not necessarily the case and in particular the anonymous authenticator requires no credentials.

The server returns a sessionId string which identifies your session and which is passed to any subsequent calls which require that you are authenticated.

A session will time out after a server determined period of time which reduces the risk of losing a sessionId. There are calls to logout, to refresh a session and to find out how much time is left and to find the username from the sessionId.

The schema"

To understand exactly how the data manipulation calls work requires an understanding of the schema. Please take a look now to make sense of the following explanation.

Each table in the database, representing a set of entities, is mapped onto a class in the API so terminology mixes OO and database concepts. Each class has uniqueness constraints, relationships and other fields. Each object is identified by a field "id" which is managed by ICAT and is returned when you create an object. This is common to all objects and is not described in the schema. The "id" field is used as the primary key in the database. There will normally be some combinations of fields, some of which may be relationships, which must be unique across all entries in the table. This is marked as "Uniqueness constraint". For Dataset this is investigation, name where investigation represents a relationship. No more than one one Dataset may exist with those two fields having the same value. These constraints are enforced by ICAT.

The relationship table is shown next. The first column shows the minimum and maximum cardinality of the relationships. A Dataset may be related to any number of DataCollectionDatasets, to at most one Sample and to exactly one DatasetType. The next column shows the name of the related class and this is followed by the name of the field which is used to represent the relationship. The basic field name is normally the name of the related class unless it is ambiguous or unnecessarily long. The field name is in the plural for "to many" relationships. The next column, "cascaded", is marked yes to show that create and delete operations are cascaded. If a Dataset is deleted then all its DataCollectionDatasets, DatasetParameters and Datafiles are deleted at the same time by one call to ICAT. In a similar manner a tree, created in memory with a Dataset having a a set of Datafiles and Datasetparameters, can be persisted to ICAT in a single call. This will be explained more later.

Note that:

relationships are all "one to many" in one direction and "many to one" in the opposite direction
all "one to many" relationships are cascaded but no "many to one" relationships
there are no other kinds of relationship in the ICAT model
all relationships are navigable in both directions

In addition each entity has four special attributes: createId, createTime, modId and modTime which are maintained by ICAT though they may be queried. For each each entity they record who created it and when, and who modified it and when.

Creating objects

Whichever interface is being used the mechanism is to create a representation of the new data object or objects on the client side and send them to the server.

long create(String sessionId, EntityBaseBean bean)

To create an object in ICAT, first instantiate the object of interest, for example a Dataset, and then call the setters to set its attributes and finally make a call to create the object in ICAT.

So typical code in Java might look like:

Dataset ds = new Dataset();
ds.setName("Name of dataset");
ds.set ...
Long dsid = icat.create(sessionId, ds);

You will see that no convenient constructors are generated, rather each field of the object must be set individually. Most fields are optional and may be left with null values, however some are compulsory and the call to create will fail if they are not set. Each object has a primary key that identifies it in the database - this is a value of type "long" that is generated by ICAT and is used to represent relationships in a regular manner.

Some fields represent attributes of the object but others are used to represent relationships. The relationships are represented in the class definitions by a variable which either holds a reference to a single object or a list of objects. In the case of a list it may be "cascaded". Consider creating a dataset with a set of datafiles. Because the relationship from dataset to datafile is cascaded they may be created in one call as outlined below:

Dataset ds = new Dataset();
ds.setName(dsName);
ds.setType(type);
Datafile datafile = new Datafile();
datafile.setDatafileFormat(format);
datafile.setName(dfName);
ds.getDatafiles().add(datafile); // Add the datafile to the dataset
icat.create(sessionId, ds);

The call to create returns the key of the created object. If you choose to write:

ds.setId(icat.create(sessionId, ds));

then the client copy of the Dataset will be updated to have the correct key value - however the keys in any other objects "within" the Dataset will still be null on the client side. In this case datafile.getId() will remain null.

When creating multiple objects in one call, the value of the cascaded flag must be noted. The line ds.getDatafiles().add(datafile) requires that the datafile is not already in the ICAT database because the cascade flag is set. If the cascaded flag is set then objects to be included in the "create" operation must not exist. However if the cascaded flag is not set then objects which are being referenced must already exist in the ICAT database.

It might help to understand what is happening when you call create. The client side object you pass in, and everything it refers to , is encoded as XML and sent to the server. There it is unpacked into the same set of objects and persisted in the database. The structure passed in must be a tree structure (or more correctly a DAG ) - if, for example, you modify the code above to create a dataset with one datafile and add datafile.setDataset(dataset) attempting to put in a reverse link which physically will appear in the ICAT database the call will be rejected by the client because you have a loop in the graph as you can then go backwards and forwards between datafile and dataset. If you passed in a proper DAG the database will create one row in the dataset table and one in the datafile table where the datafile entry includes the field datafile.dataset_id holding the dataset.id of the dataset entry just created. Relationships are represented in the database by holding the id value of the related object.